<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A religious inquisition: or, A short scrutinie after religion Wherein the large cope of true religion is narrowly inquired. By Iohn Cope, of Grayes-Inne, Esquire.</title>
            <author>Cope, John, of Gray's Inn.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19308</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118371</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853578</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853578</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18968</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19308)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18968)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1199:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A religious inquisition: or, A short scrutinie after religion Wherein the large cope of true religion is narrowly inquired. By Iohn Cope, of Grayes-Inne, Esquire.</title>
                  <author>Cope, John, of Gray's Inn.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Felix Kingston, and are to be sold by Iames Boler at the Marigold in Paules Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Princeton Theological Seminary. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18968:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18968:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELIGIOVS INQVISITION: OR, A ſhort Scrutinie after RELIGION.</p>
            <p>Wherein the large Cope of true RELIGION is narrowly <hi>inquired.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY IOHN COPE, of Grayes-Inne, ESQVIRE.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by FELIX KINGSTON, and are to be ſold by IAMES BOLER at the <hi>Marigold</hi> in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-Yard, 1629.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18968:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18968:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE, AND right vertuous Lady, ELIZABETH, Counteſſe of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had, and haue buried a good wife, ſince which time, God hath not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of me in a ſecond mariage; by reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb facs="tcp:18968:3"/> I haue not a Child of my body: being ſingle, I conuerted to my ſelfe, and (I know not how) my braine became in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and is deliuered of this (I know not what to call it:) it is not worthy the name of a booke, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept your Ladiſhip will deigne to patronage it, and giue it deſert, which fauour if your Ladiſhip indulge towards me, then my Booke like ſome meane man, that hath been entertained by ſome great perſonage, vnder
<pb facs="tcp:18968:3"/> the protection of your fauorable approbation, ſhall walk abroad with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhame of it owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthines: and my ſelfe ſhall remaine, as alwayes I ſhall haue cauſe to doe from your former large fauours:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your deuoted ſeruant,</hi> Iohn Cope.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18968:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18968:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, (for ſo you muſt be to me, if you haue patience, or will ſpend time in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo ſlight a piece of writing as this is) inſtead of an Epiſtle, I will tell you a tale, which is this. There was a yong man, who after the death of his Parents, was minded to venture his fortunes vpon the Seas, and was furniſhed as hee thought, with a prety tite veſſell, which was likewiſe fraught with commodities that were paſſable. This yong man lanched out into the Ocean, where, for a long time
<pb facs="tcp:18968:5"/> together, he had ſo faire gales of winde as his heart could deſire: thus with full ſayles he made his way thorow the deepes, but being ignorant of the paſſages of the Sea, and would not be ruled by the Pilotes, and Mariners, of which kind he had ſome that were skilfull, hee ſuddenly ranne himſelfe into a croſſe Sea; where (after hee had beene ſorely toſſed, and troubled, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the ſurging waues) his Barke began to leake, which wrought in him a ſore diſmay: but the daſhing of theſe angry bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes one againſt another, was a meanes to worke this weather-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Veſſell into a calmer Sea. This Young man reſolues to returne home, and (though with much loſſe) to deſiſt from his adventure, or to repaire his decayes; but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the narrow Seas, where
<pb facs="tcp:18968:5"/> he found a boyſterous paſſage, he diſcouered his owne Country, and knowing of a ſafe Hauen that had beene open, whence he put forth at his going to Sea, where many a tottered ſhippe had found har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, he intended to put in there: but ſo it was, through the neglect of keeping the Hauen in repaire, it was ſo choaked with quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes, that no ſhip could venture to make paſſage into it, without danger of ſhipwracke; as it fell out with this yong man, who put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to ſhore, ſplit the prore of his barke vpon a ſand. This yong man had two Iewels giuen him by his Parents, in both which they had in their lines a ioynt intereſt. At his going to Sea, he leſt one of them with his friends to keepe for him; the other he wore, tied with a ſtring about his necke next his heart; and though he had ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:18968:6"/> great loſſe, at laſt a Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man light vpon him, who finding a Iewell about his neck, that ſeemed of ſome worth, though much ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed with the beating of the ſalt water vpon it, being moued with compaſsion, tooke him into his boate, &amp; ſetting him on ſhore, holpe him to land ſo much of his goods as could be preſerued, and with much difficulty he ſaued his broken Veſſell. If the Reader deſire to know any farther meaning of this Fable, thus it is applyed: The yong man was my ſelfe, my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents knowne to be deceaſed, the Sea, was the world, the veſſell, my eſtate, as well of minde and body, as that of my outward meanes; the fraught, ſome meaſure of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, apprehenſion, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory: ſome knowledge both in humanity and diuinity: farther, my health, ſtrength of body, and
<pb facs="tcp:18968:6"/> vſe of ſences, which were good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments and part of this aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Ocean may reſemble the large ſcope I gaue my ſelfe, wherein I was carried amaine by the whiſteling gales of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of pleaſures, which did ſo fill the ſayles of my empty affections, as that I feared not to paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row any deepes of hazard. My ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the world was like, with the Yong mans vpon the Sea. The Pilots, and Mariners, whoſe direction I refuſed to follow, were ſome of my friends, that better knew the courſe of the world then my ſelfe. The croſſe Sea I fell into, was the incounter betweene proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie, and aduerſity: as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter betweene plenty and want, betweene pleaſure and trouble, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſickneſſe and health: and ſo betweene any preſent good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed, and any contrary euill that
<pb facs="tcp:18968:7"/> approacheth: and now my Barke began to leake amaine, when I could not with all the power of my vnderſtanding, body, or eſtate, ſo faſt pumpe out the waters of aduerſity, as they brake in vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, which made mee almoſt heartleſſe: yet after much toſsing and ſtruggling in vaine againſt the inſulting fury of the billowes, I was caſt vpon a calmer Sea of patience. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I reſolued to returne home to a better vnderſtanding of my ſelfe, and ſee if I could find any meanes to repaire my decay: yet when I came neere home, I found but an vnquiet paſſage tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the narrow Straights I had put my ſelfe into: how-euer, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering where I was, I adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tured to put in whence I had hoyſed ſayle, expecting harbour; but found the Young mans ſucceſſe. The two Iewels beſtowed vpon me by my
<pb facs="tcp:18968:7"/> Parents, were Religion, and a good name: the former I kept as neere my heart as I could, which yet had loſt much of its luſtre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continually daſhed vpon with the briniſh water of many corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which I paſſed thorow. The Fiſher-man that tooke mee vp, who had good knowledge of my Iewell, was ſuch a one, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt vndertooke to make his Apoſtles, fiſhers of men.</p>
            <p>Now, gentle Reader, be pleaſed out of my Fable with the moral, to take my intention in putting forth theſe few and imperfect Leaues, which is to let all that know mee vnderſtand, what my Religion is; which they may well ſuſpect ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be none, or not the right, after ſo dangerous paſſages in the world. And in the next place, my earneſt ſuite to my friends is, that (as farre as charity will moue
<pb facs="tcp:18968:8"/> them,) they would endeauour (without apparant cauſe, to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend their good word or opinion of me) to preſerue my good name; which I therefore deſire to leaue in their cuſtody. And lastly, my purpoſe in divulging theſe worthleſſe Lines, is, to tie my ſelfe by them, to the obſeruation of my owne directions: (the frailties of corrupt nature being tolerated withall:) which ſucceſſe if I find, I ſhall haue my full deſire; and ſo reſt a well-wiſher to you and all good Christians:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IOHN COPE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18968:8"/>
            <head>A SHORT SCRVTINY AFTER RELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Poets tell of a <hi>Minerua</hi> (<note place="margin">The raritie of Religion.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is vnderſtood the knowledge of Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences) begotten of <hi>Iupiters</hi> braine. The Philoſophers ſpeak of a firſt matter, which muſt be part of euery thing, and it ſelfe nothing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without forme: which matter is ſo efficacious, as nothing can bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18968:9"/> it, and yet of it ſelfe, ſo pure and ſimple, as it is not to be found in any thing. He that vndertakes to ſet forth Religion what it is, ſeemes to goe about the Fiction of a <hi>Minerua,</hi> or the deſcription of a firſt matter: for the holy Ghoſt, who is the worker of all grace in a man, may not altogether vnfitly be reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to the brayne or concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing faculty of God, as a man may with reuerence ſpeake; and this firſt matter, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is preſumed in euery man, to be in himſelfe, and yet is not to be found perfect in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 1.28. Religion perſecuted.</note>In the Euangeliſt Saint Luke, the Angell <hi>Gabriel</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> to be bleſſed amongſt women; and yet examine her condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18968:9"/> vpon earth, you ſhall hardly find a woman more miſerable; at the birth of our Sauiour ſhe had not a houſe to put her head in, but was conſtrained to take vp her Lodging in a back Stable: no ſooner was ſhee deliuered of that King (which was the cauſe why ſhe was pronounced bleſſed) but ſhee muſt fly, to ſaue her Sonnes life, into Egypt; and all the time of our Sauiours being vpon earth, was a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer with him in his perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: whilſt here ſhee liued, ſhe was ſuſpected of her beſt friend <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> of incontinency: ſince ſhe departed hence, yea to this day, is accuſed of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge, to rob God of his Worſhip, in being praied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and of blaſphemy, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18968:10"/> to command God to performe her own will. Thus fareth it with bleſſed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: when it comes into any Countrey or City, it findes euery dore ſhut againſt it, except it ſteale in at ſome backe dore, into the heart of ſome poore Chriſtian; and if it make not the more ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy flight into ſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne Countrey, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart Wilderneſſe, ſudden waight will be laid to cut off the very life of Religion; as we ſee it at this day chaſed out of its natiue countrie of Iury, and out of the ſeates of forraine Monarkes, into an Iland or two, and the confines of the earth: next, as it fell out with the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> ſo this Religion ſhall bee reputed a harlot, yea ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18968:10"/> by her owne friends, and ſupplanted by the Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet of Hereſie, if God ſhould not aſſiſt her, and that ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and blaſphemy haue been euer layd to her charge, will appeare by the accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of her aduerſaries.</p>
            <p>Neither is good and true Religion reiected as odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, impious, and erronious,<note place="margin">Religion produced for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of errors.</note> but called to the patronage of all errors, vicious liuers, &amp; wicked practices. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, becauſe he holds the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith, though ſtuffed with all manner of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he muſt be accounted Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious: the Browniſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will not endure the corruption of Church-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, though hee forſake the Church, yet he muſt be counted Religious: the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18968:11"/> the Family of loue, the Pelagians, and all the rabble of the like Heretikes, becauſe they acknowledge Chriſt, though neuer ſo full of erronious opinions, yet they muſt be accompted reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious: nay, the Turke that worſhips <hi>Mahomet;</hi> the Infidels, that worſhip the Sunne, the Moone, or other creatures; yea, ſome Nations that worſhip the Deuill him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for feare of him, becauſe they worſhippe ſomething, though neuer ſo much againſt reaſon or common ſence, yet they account themſelues to be Religious.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Religion the excuſe of wicked li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers.</note>Tell the Drunkard, that Adultery is a ſinne; he thankes God he is no adulterer, and he is of the right Religion, and he hopes it will goe well
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18968:11"/> with him. Tell the Oppeſſor, that Drunkenneſſe, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery are ſinnes; he thankes God, he is neither Drunkard, nor Adulterer, and he is of the right Religion, and hee hopes it will goe well with him. Tell the Swearer, that Drunkenneſſe, Adultery, and Oppreſſion are ſinnes; hee thankes God, he is neither Drunkard, Adulterer, nor Oppreſſor, and he is of the right Religion, and he hopes it will goe well with him. Tell any man of one ſinne in another man, that he findes himſelfe not giuen ouer vnto, though he liue in all other ſinnes, yet he hopes he is not ſo badde as that man that liues in that ſinne, and hee is of the true Religion, and hopes God will be mercifull
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18968:12"/> to him in Chriſt, &amp; it will go well with him. But there is a kinde of man that goes to Church vpon Sundayes, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues the Communion once a yeere at the leaſt, and that is at Eaſter, becauſe hereby hee hopes to goe to heauen; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues the Articles of the Creed, becauſe he is taught ſo to doe; that hopes God is mercifull, becauſe he lookes for a ſhare in his mercy; that ſweares not but ſmall oathes, becauſe to be a great ſwearer, is of ill report; that will not drinke extraordinary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is chargeable; that is very painefull and diligent in his calling, becauſe he deſires to grow rich; that keepes touch in paiment of money, becauſe he expects others ſhould doe ſo to him; or if
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18968:12"/> they do not, he will lay them as cloſe as the Priſon can keepe them; that giues to the poore at his doore, becauſe he would not be hardly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of; that hath few ſuites in Law, becauſe as neere as he can, he will wrong no body, that is either able or likely to goe to Law with him: in a word, he that liues the life of an ordinary ciuill man, and holds himſelfe to be a good Proteſtant: And this man, if you eſteeme him not a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, will thinke you doe him great wrong. And yet there is another that goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond this ciuill man, and that is hee that is vpright in his dealing for iuſtice ſake; he that is a true pay-maſter of his debts for honeſties ſake; hee that is induſtrious for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18968:13"/> Prudence ſake; he that is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteynious for tempera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſake; and he that is morally vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in any kinde (which is his Religion) for vertues ſake; who for point of faith is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with a generall beliefe, as the Church beleeues; and this man holds himſelfe to haue climed vp to a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Religion the pretence of euill practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note>Farther, what is made the colour of moſt ſedicious, blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy wars, and horrid practices, but Religion? As Sir <hi>Francis Baco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> in his Eſſayes wittily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues, they bring downe the holy Ghoſt in ſted of the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of a Doue, in the likenes of a Vulture or Rauen: &amp; out of the Barke of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſet forth the flagge of a Barke of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates. When <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Siluer-ſmith, with all his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18968:13"/> workemen, found their trade like to go downe, if the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt were receiued at Epheſus, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they cry out, that the magnifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the great goddeſſe <hi>Diana</hi> would bee deſtroyed.<note place="margin">Act. 19.27.</note> And what was pretended the cauſe of that tumultuous ſedition, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſeruation of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to their great goddeſſe <hi>Diana?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Liu. in Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riâ Romanâ, Exiſtimauit. Ancus Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Numa in pace religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſet, à ſe bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerentur, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Liuie</hi> in the Hiſtorie of the Romanes, relates of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Ancus,</hi> of the Progeny of Numa and his ſucceſſor; that when he had receiued ſome iniury from the Latines; as vnlawfull taking away the commodities of his Realme, and holding diuers of his ſubiects captiue; and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, as he thought, an inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent anſwer, vpon demand of them to be reſtored, being
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18968:14"/> minded to recouer them by warre, all his labour is to find out a faire pretence, and giue a faire challenge: and vpon theſe conſiderations he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnes: that ſince his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor <hi>Numa</hi> had founded Religion in peace, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned him to ground his warre vpon Religion; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon his Ambaſſador being diſpatched with Commiſſion to proclaime warre,<note place="margin">Audi, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter, ego ſum pulib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus nuncius populi Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni: iuſtè pié<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> venio: ſi ego impiè illos ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines dedier, nuncio populi Romani mihi expoſco, tum Patriae compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem me nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſinas eſſe, haec qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque ei ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius fuit, haec portum ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diens, haec fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ingreſſus peragit.</note> thus runs his meſſage: Heare, O <hi>Iupiter,</hi> I am ſent by the generall conſent of the Roman peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and that what I do as Ambaſſador, is iuſt and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious; I call thee to witneſſe, and if I do herein vniuſtly, or impiouſly; then neuer ſuffer me to be a man thought fit for ſeruice, or worthy regard in my Country: and theſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18968:14"/> things the Legate buzzed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euery mans eare that met him; thinking that when hee had made Religion the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of his Maſters warre, and inuoked God, that then hee might fairely denounce warre, for the effecting of his particular end. When the Phariſes were almoſt ready to burſt with malice againſt our Sauiour Chriſt, and could finde no reſt within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, till they had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that deuilliſh, matchleſſe, and colourleſſe murther vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: (for <hi>Pilate</hi> confeſſeth he could find no cauſe,) they pretend he was a Sabbath-breaker, he was a Deuill, hee was a Blaſphemer, he was a mouer of Sedition: and theſe things could not be tolerated in their Religion; &amp; therefore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18968:15"/> away with him, crucifie him, crucifie him. So that here the maintenance of Religion, is the cloak of this horrible fact. But there are too many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of later dayes before our eyes, of this truth. What vnſheathed the ſword of ſo many Maſſacrers in France not long ſince, to the taking away of ſo many Chriſtian ſoules in one night? They will tell you, Religion. What gaue boldneſſe to that deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Villaine, to make his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes, the late King of France his bowels, the Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berd for his poiſon'd dagger? If he were aliue, he would tell you, Religion. What ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the wits, and ſteeled the hearts of our Engliſhmen lately; that if there had bene a Councell called in Hell, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18968:15"/> a company of grand Diuels ſent vpon earth, for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of their deſignes, they could not haue found out a more damnable Plot, nor with greater reſolution haue proſecuted it, then they did the Gun-powder Treaſon? All their excuſe would be, that it was in the cauſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. What hath plucked of late, the louing Husband from his Wifes tender im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, the beloued Sonne from his Parents carefull go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, the diligent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, from his Maſters ſerious imployment; and the Loyall ſubiect from his Kings peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Dominions; and all from their natiue Country, either to make way for their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes, thorow the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of men, women, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18968:16"/> or expoſe themſelues to vnauoydable ſlaughter? Is it not, becauſe men pretend Religion the colour of their warre, though they intend nothing but the getting of ſome Towne or Country? So that looke into men of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and conditions, you ſhall find euery man claime an intereſt in Religion; and yet how hard a thing it is, to find ſincere and true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on planted in any Nation (our owne excepted,) or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar mans heart? Wherefore it is not altogether vnexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for a man, as well as hee may, to informe himſelfe, what true Religion is.</p>
            <p>Some will haue the word, Religion, to be deriued from a Latine word,<note place="margin">Rĕlĕgo.</note> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, to reade ouer againe, or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18968:16"/> to remember: but this ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to bee ſo proper a deriuation; becauſe reading is an act of the tongue, and conuerſant aſwell about falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, as truth: and Religion is chiefly ſeated in the mind, and imbraceth nothing but truth. Againe, for remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, it is of ſomthing fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt: but neuer man yet knew what belonged to Religion, before it is wrought in him by the holy Ghoſt; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot remember that, of which hee neuer had ſo much as a notion. Farther, if it ſhould haue this former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuation, it ſhould onely inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate a bare remembrance of a thing, and no way giue light to the nature of the thing.</p>
            <p>There is a word which more fitly offers it ſelfe, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18968:17"/> ſignifies in Latine,<note place="margin">Religo. Auguſt. de vera relig. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligat ergo nos vera religio v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni omnipotenti Deo, vnde reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio dicta eſt.</note> to bind or tye. True Religion, ſayes an ancient Writer, doth tye vs to the onely and Almightie God; and from this tying doth Religion take its name. <hi>Adam</hi> had no ſooner tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the commandement of God, but takes his flight, ſeekes ſhelter vnder the trees of the Garden, to hide him ſelfe from the preſence of the Lord God: but when God apprehends him with his cal, there is no longer keeping out. <hi>Adam</hi> being arraigned, and hauing receiued the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of his puniſhment, hee might yet bee like to many children or ſeruants, that when they haue once gotten a cuſtome of running away from their Fathers or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, they ſhall neuer keepe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18968:17"/> them at home, without they ſhackle, or tie them faſt; and therfore God, to preuent this runnagacy in <hi>Adam</hi> and his poſteritie, hath prouided this bond of Religion, to tie them faſt to himſelfe, as the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father ſayes.<note place="margin">Ierem. ſuper nonum cap. Amos. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia eſt faſcicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, vnâ Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini religione conſtrictus, vnde &amp; ipſa religio à reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gando &amp; in faſcem domini vinciendo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men accepit.</note> The Church, ſayes another, is a bundle tyed together with the wreath of Religion; whence, ſaies he, religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> takes the name from binding. Till the comming of our bleſſed Sauiour, the Church of God was only amongſt the Iewes: but they, when he came into the world, refuſed ſubiection to him. Whereupon our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord ſends his Apoſtles throughout all the World, to gather vp, as it were, heere a ſticke, and there a Chriſtian ſticke; which being preſented
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18968:18"/> to God, hee makes a bundle, and tyes it vp with this wreath of Religion, and ſo hath made himſelfe a new Church: and this latter word, binding, giues ſome inſight into the nature of Religion; which is either a binding to, or a binding from a thing: a binding to, is a binding to faith and obedience; a bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to faith in all that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in Gods Word, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to all that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Gods Word: the binding from, is from all er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and hereſie in point of doctrine, contrary to Gods Word; and from all impiety in courſe of life, forbidden by Gods Word. And this latter deriuation of the word, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſeemes to make it more full: for as in the word, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctation,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18968:18"/> which ſignifies a ſtrife or ſtrugling, there is an oppoſition implyed; ſo this aduerbe, <hi>re,</hi> in religion, doth ſeeme to intimate an auerſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the nature of man, to what hee is required vnto by the Word of God. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon conſequently followes a third tye, or binding, which is to repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for the prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mans nature to euery thing, contrary to Gods will, and the wicked actions hee cannot chuſe but fall into, out of that naturall and depraued inclination.<note place="margin">Caluin. in <hi>23.</hi> cap. Iob. Iobus adijcit ſe non ab ea receſſiſſe: eo ſignifica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines ſemper pru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itis quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam deflecten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di à recta via ſollicitari.</note> To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Caluin,</hi> in his coment vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 23. Chapter of <hi>Iob,</hi> out of <hi>Iob's</hi> reſolution to walke in the way of God, adding theſe words, that he had not gone out of the ſame, hath this obſeruation, that there is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18968:19"/> a certaine kind of itching de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in euery man, to ſwerue and decline from that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine way; and therefore he had neede to be kept in with this hedge of Religion.</p>
            <p>There are three words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, which the Grecians haue giuen, to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie Religion: the one ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies right or true worſhip.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> It is not enough to haue knowledge, nor to beleeue in God, though theſe are neuer ſeuered from Religion: but there muſt be a worſhip, and this worſhip muſt not be eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie worſhip, but a true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Another of theſe words ſignifies the worſhip of God;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſo that in this name of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is included a worſhip, but not the worſhip of man, or any other creature; but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18968:19"/> the worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>The third word is thought to take its deriuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the name of the Thracians,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 27. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and is vſed by the Apoſtle in the firſt Chapter of <hi>Iames</hi> his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle. But becauſe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteſt knowledge man can haue of any thing, is from the cauſes thereof, therefore it will not be amiſſe for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the nature of Religion, to inquire into the cauſes of it more at large; ſom of which are ſhortly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the words before.</p>
            <p>Amongſt cauſes,<note place="margin">God the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cauſe of Religion.</note> the effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe takes the firſt place, as well does this efficient of Religion deſerue it, which was truly the firſt, yea, before the firſt thing in the World; God was before all things:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.2.</note> ſo that the efficient cauſe, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18968:20"/> worker of true Religion, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a publike eſtate, or priuate mans heart, is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then God himſelfe: God is the worker of all grace;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.17.</note> all good giftes proceede from aboue. And Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> one of the maſter-workemen in this plantation of Religion, hath theſe words in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Corinthians;<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>No man can ſay, that Ieſus is the Lord, but by the Spirit. There are diuerſities of gifts, but the ſame Spirit: there are differences of adminiſtrations, but the ſame Lord: and there are diuerſities of operations, but it is the ſame God that worketh all in all.</hi> In <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel,</hi> God firſt vndertakes to clenſe them of their falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but leaues them not there; for then they were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the neerer; but in the next
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18968:20"/> words ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27.</note> 
               <hi>A new heart will I giue you, and alſo a new Spirit will I put within you; and I will put my Spirit within you, and cauſe you to walke in my Statutes:</hi> ſo that God takes to himſelfe the worke of framing them to true Religion; and the whole Scripture is very full of proofes to this purpoſe. There was a worthy man, who out of his obſeruation vpon theſe words of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour; I am the way, the truth and the life; brought in Chriſt ſpeaking to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſoule in this manner,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in tract. <hi>22.</hi> Ambulare vis? Ego ſum via. Falli non vis? Ego ſum veritas. Mori non vis? Ego ſum vita. haec dicit Saluator tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, Non eſt quò eas niſi ad me, non eſt qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eas niſi per me.</note> and anſwering himſelf; Wilt thou walke (ſaith Chriſt?) I am the way. Wilt thou not be deluded? I am the truth. Wilt thou not die? I am the life. This (ſaith the learned Man) is the ſpeech of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18968:21"/> to this ſilly ſoule: Thou haſt not whither to goe, but to me; nor any way to come to me, but by me: ſo that if we will walke in the way of Religion, we muſt walk with Chriſt, for he is the way; if wee will not bee ſeduced by errour, which is contrarie to Religion, we muſt be direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him, for he is the truth: if wee will liue religiouſly here, and gloriouſly hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; we muſt liue by him, and in him, and he in vs, for hee is the life. The ſame Author ſayes in another place;<note place="margin">Ipſum donum Dei Spiritus cum Patre &amp; Filio aequè in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mutabile co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere &amp; tenere nos conuenit.</note> Wee ought to imbrace the gift of the Spirit of God, equally diſpenſed and vnchangeable from the Father and the Son.</p>
            <p>Another reuerend Father ſayes in his Comment vpon the firſt Chap. of <hi>Amos,</hi> vpon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18968:21"/> theſe words: <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierom, ſuper primum cap. Amos; Deus verſatur in vera religione, non in Jſrael vrbibus.</note> 
               <hi>or the Lord will roare from Sion, and vtter his voyce from Ieruſalem.</hi> God is conuerſant (ſaies he) in true Religion profeſſed in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, not in the Cities of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. So that from both theſe may be gathered, that as Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is the gift of God, yea, of the whole Trinitie: ſo where Religion is, God is; &amp; where he is not, there is no true Religion; and from that that doth precede, the concluſion will eaſily ariſe, that God is the efficient cauſe of religion.</p>
            <p>Neither is he only the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,<note place="margin">God, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly efficient cauſe.</note> but the onely effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe. Man is a meere patient. No, not ſo much as a patient: for all matter is held to haue an aptitude, or an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, or at leaſt, a poſſibilitie to receiue a forme. But ſuch
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18968:22"/> is the indiſpoſition of mans depraued nature, that it hath no capacity, nay, it hath a contrary affection to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the forme of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which God puts vpon him. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the Romanes ſaith;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.</note> that <hi>the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh is enmity againſt God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> where the word is very expreſſe, and ſignifies the beſt thoughts and affections; the ſame Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to the Epheſians, ſaith, that <hi>all men by nature are dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1.</note> And in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to the Philippians; <hi>It is God that worketh both the will and the deed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13.</note> 
               <note place="margin">In orat. pro Marco Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cello. Bellicas laudes ſolent quidam extenuare verbis, eáſque communicare cum militibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> propriae ſint Imperatorum, &amp; certè in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis millitum virtus, loco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas, multum iuuant: maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam verò partem quaſi ſuo iure for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna ſibi ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> in one of his Orations, commends <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> aboue all things for his clemency, becauſe that was his proper glory, &amp; his only. In his victories, he tells him,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18968:22"/> he ſhould haue ſharers; the Captaines and common ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers would euery one claym his ſhare; yea, a great part of the glory of thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſts would bee aſcribed to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience of the place, or to <hi>Fortune:</hi> but for his clemency, none could chalenge any part of that glory. So for outward workes, as building of hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, planting of Vineyards and Orchards, husbanding of the earth, ordering and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of creatures, yea, and gouerning of nations (though God indeed be the giuer and gouernour of all; and it is his bleſſing that makes all things vſefull, and commodious to man, and ſo excludes <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune;</hi>) yet in theſe things, hee hath giuen man leaue to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe his owne iudgement
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18968:23"/> and induſtry, &amp;, as it were, to ſhare with him in his prayſe: but for the working of Grace and Religion, whereby hee largely expreſſeth his cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency to man, there is none either admitted, or able to ioyne with him. A King hath certaine prerogatiues reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to himſelfe; as ſealing of his Patents, ſtamping of his Coyne, chuſing of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, creating of his Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the like: So God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of no Parents for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, without they haue his broad Seale of Religion; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes no Chriſtian for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, except he haue his ſtamp of Religion; and whoſoeuer ſhall counterfeite either of theſe, is guiltie of high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: and as no man can chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to be the Kings ſeruant
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18968:23"/> out of his owne deſert, but holds himſelfe highly regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the King, in being called to his ſeruice; and likewiſe expects continuall meanes from the King, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him to ſerue him: So in this ſpirituall ſeruice of God, there is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worthy of him ſelfe, neither hath he inward abilitie to maintaine himſelfe in the place that God calles him vnto, without a ſupply of grace from God, which worketh in him this Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And ſo to bee a Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of heauen, is out of Gods meere fauour; and as you ſhall ſee in a meane man, created a Nobleman, a great alteration in his behauiour, in his ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, in his actions, in his whole carriage; yea, in his mind he hath thoſe thoughts,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18968:24"/> now hee is a Peere to the King, that neuer came into his head before: ſo more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly you may diſcerne in a Chriſtian man, a great change throughout body and ſoule, whoſe baſe nature is turned into a truly noble diſpoſition, deſpiſing the traſh of the earth, and all ſeruile conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and aimeth only to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelfe in a religious courſe of life to his Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, Ieſus Chriſt, to whom hee is now made a Peere. Kings, when they make fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, for the moſt part, chuſe ſuch as are of ſmall meanes, and an ordinary ranke, that the greater glory might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to themſelues; for therein they ſomthing ſeeme to reſemble God in his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who made all things out
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18968:24"/> of nothing: ſo theſe make a great man out of nothing, in compariſon of what he is rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to. Thus God in his work of regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, finds ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> void of grace or religion, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to himſelf the effecting of theſe things in him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is made a Child and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorite of God; and yet in this worke, doth not take from a man his humanitie, &amp; naturall abilities; but ſo frames theſe, as they ſhal become conduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to this effect, though no way operatiue; neither doth this giue any way to free-wil, that there is a vſe of the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of will in man, yea, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. When a man is ſaid to haue no free will, it is not to be conceiued in naturall actions; as to goe, or ſtand ſtill; to ſpeake, or to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18968:25"/> be ſilent; to doe this thing, or not to do it, as a natural actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; or that the vſe of the ſences is not common &amp; free to good and bad men, as ſeeing, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, &amp; the like; or that a man hath no power in morall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as to be temperate, &amp; iuſt in his dealings, &amp; liberall, and the like; or in the outward acts of Eccleſiaſticall duties; as to go to Church, to receiue the Sacrament, and do things of that nature; or to forbeare the outward practice of ſome ſins; as a drunkard, or a ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer may be hired not to drink, or ſweare for a time, &amp; yet in none of theſe, is to be found freewill to grace, which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to be in a man, and that is to be able out of his own free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, to do theſe naturall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and obſerue theſe morall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18968:25"/> duties, &amp; all other Religious duties, or forbeare euil, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Word of God, and in obedience to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: for ſin is a breach of the Law, and therefore, to doe good,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is to doe what man does in obedience to the Law, which no man can doe of himſelfe, but muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a new forme put vpon him; and himſelfe, and that naturall will, which is in its ſelfe actiue, muſt be meerely paſſiue: wherein is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the Papiſt and the Proteſtant: the one ſayes a man doth cooperate with the Spirit: the other, that the Spirit workes all, and that a man is a meere pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient. In the beginning of the world God made a Coas, a rude indigeſted ſubſtance,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18968:26"/> which had an actiue power in it ſelfe, but in relation to the ſeuerall formes God put vpon it, was a meere patient. So plants haue a vegetatiue and growing forme, but in regard of that ſenſitiue forme, which in all ſenſitiue liuing creatures, this vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue ſubſtance is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, but as the matter of the enſuing ſenſitiue crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and that ſenſitiue ſoule is but meerely paſſiue, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the reaſonable ſoule wherewith God informes a man. So is it with a man, he hath naturall power ouer his body, and in many morall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, is able to put them in practice: but to attaine to Grace, he hath no abilitie nor will, but is a meere patient to the worke of the Spirit.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18968:26"/> The grand Patron of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh profeſſion,<note place="margin">Bellar. in li. <hi>3.</hi> de gratia, &amp; libero arbitrio.</note> hath gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a definition of Free-will, out of the doctrine of one of the chiefe<note n="a" place="margin">Ex doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae S. Thomae definitio col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecta. Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum arbitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, eſt libera p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teſtas ex his quae ad finem conducunt, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num prae alio eligendi, aut vnum &amp; idem acceptandi, vel pro arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio reſpuendi, intelligenti naturae ad magnam Dei gloriam attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buta.</note> Schoolemen, which is this; that Freewill is a free power of chuſing one of thoſe things which tend to an end before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or accepting or reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting out of its owne power, one and the ſame thing, and is attributed to an intelligent or reaſonable nature: for the great glory of God, who ſhortly analiſing, or opening this definition,<note n="b" place="margin">Liberum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrium eſt po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentia, non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitus vel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, quae po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia eſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus &amp; libera differentia, &amp; quia potentia omnis eſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidens ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum liberi arbitrij, eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligens na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura, obiectum liberi arbitrij eſt ex his quae ad finem conducunt. Siquidem liberum arbitrium non verſatur circa finem, ſed media: electio eſt proprius actus liberi arbitrij.</note> ſayes, that Free-will is a power, not a habit or act; and after he hath aſſigned power to be the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> or materiall cauſe, and an intelligent nature to be the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18968:27"/> ſubiect of it, and the meanes conuerſant about the end, not the end it ſelfe to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of it, concludes at laſt, that Election is the proper act of Free-will: where, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that he brings in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription for a definition, he ſeemes to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that which before he ſaid, to be neither habit nor act, but a meere power to be actiue in Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But admit him, that a bare power is the materiall cauſe, or the <hi>genus</hi> of Free-will: yet there is a learned Father will ſoone make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that this power is none of mans: for, ſaith he,<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. in ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſitione <hi>12.</hi> Cap. Euang. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannis: Ne exiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus fidem noſtram eſſe in libero arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio, vt diuino non aegeat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d intorio: audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſtam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem, Dedit eis poteſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Filios Dei fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</note> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Free-will, let vs heare the Euangeliſt, ſaying, God gaue them power to bee made the ſonnes of God. So that this power ſpoken of, is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18968:27"/> the gift and Grace of God. And admit the Papiſt thus much, that man doth coöpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate with the Spirit, as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diuines hold, a rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate man doth, yet this is no argument to proue Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, becauſe a man may coö<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate without power of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Neither yet is man to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend altogether vpon this inward worke of God:<note place="margin">The Word, the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental cauſe of Religion.</note> for he hath appointed his Word as an inſtrument of this bleſſed effect of Religion; and this Word is a plentifull Store-houſe of all inſtruments of Religion. The inſtruments of a ſouldier, are his armes. Let the ſpirituall Souldier go to <hi>Paul,</hi> one of the chiefe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in that Armory, and hee will furniſh him from head,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18968:28"/> to toe,<note place="margin">Eph. 6. Chap. 14, 15, 16, 17. verſes.</note> with the Helmet of Saluation, the Breſtplate of Righteouſneſſe, the Girdle of Verity, the Shield of Faith, the Sword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the Shooes of the preparation of the Goſpell. The inſtruments of a ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, are his bookes. Let the Scholler in Gods Schoole, or Vniuerſity, reſort to this Library of the Word, and there he ſhall finde ſuch Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, as is beyond all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Writers in that kinde; ſuch Hiſtory, as makes all other Hiſtorians that meddle with the ſame ſubiect, for point of truth, liers; and for Antiquity, nouices: ſuch profound Propheſies verified by the performance of euery the leaſt tittle, as make all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther propheſies appeare fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18968:28"/> ſuch Diuine Poetry, as makes all other Poets ſeeme bunglers, being compared with the ſweete Singer of Iſrael, and the Wiſe Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: ſuch elegancy, that if you looke into <hi>Eſay,</hi> you ſhall find ſuch a lofty ſtile, as is in no other booke but the Scripture. If you looke into the other Prophets, you ſhall find ſuch hidden Rethoricke, as is no where to be found, but in holy Writ: if you looke into our Bleſſed Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours ſpeeches, you ſhall find ſuch Metaphors, and Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and Wiſe ſayings, as confounded all that roſe vp to ſpeake againſt him, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed all that heard him: if you looke into S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logeticall Orations, you ſhall find the famous Orator <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullus</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:18968:29"/> put to ſilence,<note place="margin">Act. 24.10.</note> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>med to pleade any more againſt him; and <hi>Felix</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, trembling at what hee ſpake. But laſt of all, in his holy Word, you ſhall find ſuch Diuinity, as whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer vndertakes to ſet forth the excellency of it, ſhall giue it a blemiſh; and when man hath beaten his braine to the vttermoſt, he muſt breake forth onely into ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, and ſay; Oh, the height, the depth, and the bredth of this vnſearcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Myſtery of Diuinitie! The Inſtruments of a builder are his tooles: and here in this Word, the Chriſtian builder ſhall find a Maſons hammer, to rough how the hard heart of man, and a two-edged ſword, more ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>llent for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18968:29"/> that purpoſe, then any Saw to cut aſunder the ſtony heart of man, and a Square to leuell and ſhape a man to ſome fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for this ſpirituall buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. There are two maine Pillers of Religion, vpon which if it be firmely ſettled, it cannot ſinke, and that is a well-grounded faith, and a well-ordered life. And how to eſtabliſh Religion vpon theſe two, that Famous <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine</hi> will teach a man. For the firſt, in his Comment vpon the twelfth Pſalme, where he askes the queſtion, whether or no at any time there do ſteale into a mans minde, any doubt of beleeuing in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God? which if there do, then he directs him how to fence himſelfe againſt ſuch a temptation, Let him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18968:30"/> ſayes he,<note place="margin">Cal. in Com. <hi>12.</hi> Pſalm. Quoties de fide promiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Dei ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repit aliqua dubitatio, ſtatim hunc clipeum oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere conuenit ſermones Dei eſſe puros. Cal. in Com. <hi>23.</hi> Cap. Iob, Diſcamus bene &amp; rectè vtuendi ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, quam Deus nobis probat, hanc eſſe vt pedes p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>namus in via, quam non ipſi inſtitui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſed ipſe nobis verbo ſuo common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrauit.</note> take this into his hand for a ſhield or buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, that all the words of God are pure. And for the ſecond, how to frame a mans life, in his Comment vpon the 23. Chap. of <hi>Iob,</hi> he giues this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: Let a man learne this to be the courſe which God doth allow of liuing well and vprightly, namely, to ſet his feete in a way, not ſuch a one as he ſhall propoſe to himſelfe, but ſuch a one as God ſhall ſhew vnto him out of his Word: neither doth God vſe this inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall cauſe of the Word, in working Religion in a man, as though hee needed it: for he was as well able, after the fall of man, to haue made him perfectly good againe, as he was before: but God ſaw
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18968:30"/> this the fitteſt way: and ſome reaſon may be giuen to the apprehenſion of man, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him ſo much.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> As that firſt, man might take notice of the grieuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and greatneſſe of his ſinne in his fall, which had plunged him into ſuch miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as he knew no way how to get out of it, except God had found a meanes for him how to eſcape, which, peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, had God reſtored him to his former integritie, would not haue taken ſo deepe an impreſſion in him as now it doth, when he is faine to labour and take paines in the meanes, and eſpecially the Word of God, which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man muſt do.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, God might vſe this meanes of the Word, to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18968:31"/> let man know his infinit loue vnto him, in ſending his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Sonne Ieſus Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, to ſuffer for man: and our inſtruction in this point, is the ſcope of the whole Scripture; which Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Sauiour had not needed, if God had ſuddenly ſettled man in his former vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, God may take this courſe, that a man may haue ſome comfort to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in working out his owne Saluation, by the meanes. And this ſaluation is the end of Religion; not that a man doth exerciſe any power of his owne in the worke either of Religion, or ſaluation, farther then to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and ſubiect himſelfe to the meanes; but God would
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18968:31"/> haue man to ſee the depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of all parts, inward, and outward, and worke them through the efficacy of the Word, to incline to Grace, &amp; ſo to temper them, as to yeeld to the impreſſion of Religion; with which the Holy Ghoſt is ſealing him vp to eternall life. This cannot but bring a great deale of ſweete comfort to the heart of man, which would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be loſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, God may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the rather worke by his Word, becauſe man might exerciſe all thoſe good gifts which God gaue him in his creation; as meditation, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, affection, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, for the vſe of all which, a man ſhall receiue direction out of the Word; whereas if
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18968:32"/> a man had beene made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect againe, he ſhould haue had onely a willing and a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine contemplation and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and neuer haue nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the bent or intention of his minde, as now he doth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, Gods end in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining the chiefe meanes of a mans ſaluation, to bee his Word, wherein man muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour all the dayes of his life, may be, that man may bee brought to a higher eſteeme of Heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, God may doe this, to expreſſe his Iuſtice, that thoſe who wilfully periſh, hauing the meanes of the Word offered them, may be left without excuſe, and their deſtruction may be on their owne heads.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Worſhip the materiall cauſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note>Now it hath beene decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18968:32"/> that God alone is the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and the Word, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall cauſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. The next cauſe is,<note place="margin">Worſhip, the materiall cauſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> the materiall cauſe of Religion, and that is Worſhip. The Pſalmiſt ſayes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.17.</note> The Eyes of all things looke vp and wayte vpon thee: and in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place,<note place="margin">Pſal. 148.1.</note> calls vpon the Heauens, and all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to praiſe the Lord; which waiting, and praiſing may be taken as part of the worſhip of God: but as for vnſenſible creatures, they on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are ſaid to praiſe God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſet forth his praiſe: for ſenſible creatures, as in many things they ſeeme to haue that reaſon which is onely in a man, in chuſing or refuſing good or euill for themſelues: yet this is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18968:33"/> but an inward inſtinct, without the diſcourſe of the mind. In theſe creatures, there is a kinde of expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, of good things; and an inward cheerefulnes, which is a kinde of acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, or thankſgiuing for good things receiued, and likewiſe, a patient mourning, or humiliation, as a man may ſay, vnder the hand of God, when they want his gifts, (wherein they may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne many men that are ready to murmur, vpon the withdrawing of the leaſt of Gods mercies,) yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not this by the direction of reaſon, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be properly called wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>There are diuers words which haue ſometimes, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18968:33"/> in ſome places, as well in Scriptures, as other writers, an equiualent or promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſignification, and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, a more diſtinct conſtruction; as the ſame words,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which in the Greeke tongue more properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify worſhip, and honor, and ſeruice, are vſed all of them oftentimes, and in ſeuerall places, to expreſſe one and the ſame thing; and each of them ſignifies the ſame that any one of them does; as in the Worſhip of God, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood and compriſed his Honour, and Seruice; and in his Honour, his Worſhip and Seruice; and in his Seruice, his Worſhip and Honour.</p>
            <p>Now this matter of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which is Worſhip, or Honour, is found to be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18968:34"/> to man, to Angels, and to Idols. To man, when the ſame words are vſed to ſet forth the reuerence or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect a child oweth to his Parents, or an inferior to a ſuperior, or any man to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for any extraordinary gift, that are vſed to expreſſe the Honour of God. The words of the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are, that a child ſhould honour his Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and in the Poem of <hi>Phocilides,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> children are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted in the firſt place, to honour God, and in the next place, their Parents. <hi>Paul,</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17.</note> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, that the Elders that rule well, ſhould be accounted worthy of double honour. And <hi>Xenophon</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that the Rulers vnder <hi>Cyrus</hi> worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18968:34"/> him, or reuerenced him as a Father.<note place="margin">Lib. de beata vita: Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem vt Deos, &amp; eius pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſores, vt antiſtites co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite.</note> 
               <hi>Seneca</hi> would haue men to worſhip vertue, as the gods themſelues; and the Profeſſors of it, as the Antiſtites, which were the chief Prieſts of the Temples, and were ouerſeers, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of all things that did belong to the worſhip of the gods.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> In <hi>Pithagoras</hi> is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a worſhip, or worthy eſteeme of the vnmarried; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating an extraordinarie kinde of reuerence to bee giuen to them, that had ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch a gift of continence, or power to keepe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in a chaſt courſe of life vnmarried. This worſhip is likewiſe aſcribed to Angels, as a worthy Writer hath not long ſince obſerued.<note place="margin">Beza, <hi>2.</hi> Cap. ad Coloſ. Eſt forma Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis, quae ex ſpeculatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rioſis, &amp; tamen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conditae cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſdam ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men habenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus oritur, cruuſmodi eſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> There is a worſhip (ſaith he) which
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18968:35"/> ariſeth out of curious ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, which yet makes a ſhew of certaine hidden wiſedome; of which ſort, is the worſhip of Angels. And <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Reuelation is ſaid, To offer worſhip to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel. Laſtly, this worſhip or ſeruice, is attributed to Idols, as the word Idolatry will teach,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which ſignifies the worſhip of Idols. The firſt of theſe acceptions of worſhip or honour, a it is applied to a man, is allowable; the other two acceptions, as worſhip, is attributed to Angels &amp; Idols: the former of them requires a cautelous conſtruction, leſt it proue derogatorie to Gods Worſhip, and implies a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy regard of them, for their excellent nature and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: the latter, is abſolutely
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18968:35"/> ſinfull, and directly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by God himſelf. Whence may be gathered a threefold diſtinction of worſhip, which is either a reuerend and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectfull eſteeme of ſome creature, out of any duty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them; or any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall excellency in them, which may be expreſſed in a mans outward carriage; or ſuch an application of a mans ſeruice to an Idoll, as that he ſets it in the place of God: or laſtly, the worſhip which God challengeth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; and thus worſhip, or honour may be ſaid in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to be giuen, as well to the creature as to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</p>
            <p>But it is the forme of euery thing that giues it being.<note place="margin">The truth of worſhip to God-ward, the formall cauſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> Now the forme of this Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18968:36"/> may be taken to conſiſt in two things. In the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and in the truth of that Worſhip. Here is not meant that forme ſpoken of by <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> which a man may haue, and yet deny the power of Religion; but that forme which is power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to make a man truly reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, &amp; muſt informe a man what Religion is. So that he that will be religious, muſt worſhip God, and that in Trueth. Firſt, he muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God. And what is God? Himſelfe tels vs, that his Name is,<note place="margin">Exod. 3.14.</note> I AM, and Chriſt, in the Goſpell of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.58.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked of the Iewes; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had ſeene <hi>Abraham,</hi> being not yet fifty yeers old, does not anſwer them; That before <hi>Abraham</hi> was, I was:
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18968:36"/> but ſaid vnto them; before <hi>Abraham</hi> was, I AM. And what is he? That I AM, ſaies God; and that is All, and that All, is All. Let a man mount vpon the wings of cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (which is ſwifter then any flying bird,) into the higheſt Heauen, which is the Seate of Gods incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Maieſtie; and there ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine an vnimaginable glory; that He is: let him come downe into the Firmament; and (if he can without daze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,) looke vpon that orient Ruby, and that ſplendent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amond, the bigger, and leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer light, round beſet with the ſparkling Starres; all which doe as much excell in operatiue vertue, the moſt precious Stone the Earth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foordes, as there is diſtance
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18968:37"/> betweene heauen and earth: and that He is. Let him paſſe thorow the element of fire, and there make a little ſtay, where he ſhall ſtand in the middeſt of fire, and not burne, nor be ſenſible of the heate, if hee were bodily there; which fire ſets on fire all other bodies, and that He is. Let him make a ſtep lower into the element of Aire, and there hee ſhall finde ſuch a friendly diſcord, as that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moiſture ſhall quench heate, nor heate dry vp moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture; without temperature, no liuing creature could breathe: and that He is. Let him take a iourny to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt parts of the earth, and where-euer he comes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of God, and there hee ſhall here of Him; for <hi>the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18968:37"/> earth and the fulneſſe thereof is the Lords.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 24.1.</note> Let him diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend into the Store-houſe of the earth, and ſearch the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Cabinets of Gods Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, and the whole Treaſury of his Riches, and there hee is to be found:<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.5.</note> 
               <hi>For he hath laid the foundation of the earth.</hi> Let him go downe into the deepes of the water, and there take view of Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; which are for number incredible, and many of them for ſhape, proportion, and condition, accounted Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: and likewiſe thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that common benefit, which all liuing creatures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue from this element of water (without which they could not ſubſiſt,) and there he ſhall vnderſtand of Him; they are the words of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18968:38"/> Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 135.6.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoeuer pleaſed the Lord, that did he in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and in the earth, and in the ſea.</hi> And when a man hath taken a ſight of the Mycro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme, or great world, and receiued ſome apprehenſion of God therein, let him caſt his eye vpon that Mycro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme, or little world him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, wherein is as much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, and compacted, as is conteined in the whole Vniuerſe: and ſee if there hee can receiue any farther infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of God. There a man ſhall ſee (as it were the Sunne and Moone,) vnderſtanding, and ſence, placed in the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt and ſphericall part of his body. The opinion of the Naturaliſt is, that the Sunne and a man generate a man,<note place="margin">Sol &amp; homo genera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> which in this fabricke
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18968:38"/> is true; that the ſunne of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding working vpon the terrene and elementary parts of a man, makes vp a man, and withall, this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Heauenly Planet ſends forth light and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whereby the whole man is continually directed and preſerued. Here likewiſe may bee obſerued the Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidian motion of this Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, which daily viſiteth the whole man with ſweete comfort and illumination, and the annuall motion, like vnto that yeerely progreſſe of the Sunne, wherein it takes a more particular and ſerious view of all the parts of the Earth. And indeed it is a good yeeres worke, for the ſwifteſt contemplation, to take an exact conſideration
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18968:39"/> of all the faculties and parts of a man, and that inward, and eſtimatiue ſence, which is called by ſome, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence, and repreſents the Moone, receiues all the light it hath from the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, whence commeth the Eclipſe; as may be ſaid of this Moone within a man, when the earthly, carnall, and externall parts of a man, are interpoſed betweene ſence, and the light of the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; and the like eclipſe is there of the Sunne, which is reſembled by the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, when ſence inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth it ſelfe betweene a man, and true reaſon. Let a man looke into the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoughts and cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, which are in number and quality, like the twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18968:39"/> Starres of Heauen, whereof ſome are fixed, but moſt wandering; and hee ſhall eaſily diſcerne a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude betweene the things compared, which is likewiſe to be found in the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of a man. The ſhape of a man, as long as he is contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the round wombe of his Mother, is Globary, till that diuine part of him be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, which requires a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtike, and commanding ſtature: ſince God hath ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected all the creatures vnder his gouernement; which is liuely expreſſed by <hi>Ouid</hi> the Poet, who hauing ſet forth the Creation of the world, with the creatures inhabiting therein, proceeds with words to this purpoſe; There was yet wanting, (ſaith hee) a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18968:40"/> more perfect and ſacred li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing creature that ſhould bee capable of tranſcendent knowledge,<note place="margin">Ouid. Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morph. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Sanctius his animal, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> capacius altae, Deerat ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc, &amp; quod dominari in caetera poſſet. Natus homo eſt, Prora<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cùm ſpectent ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malia caetera terram, Os homini ſublime dedit, coelùmque videre, Iuſſit, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectos ad ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra tollere vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</note> and might beare rule ouer all other things. Man was borne: and whereas all other creatures were fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, with their eyes caſt downe vpon the earth; God gaue man a lofty counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and an vpright and ſtately proportion, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him to looke vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, from whence he came. But the elements retaine the ſame qualities and oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the body of a man, which they had before this compoſition; for heate, and coldneſſe, and moiſture, and drineſſe are in continuall ſtrife, which ſhall haue the predominancy; and which is a ſtrange thing, this diſcord
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18968:40"/> is a cauſe both of the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and deſtruction of the ſame ſubiect: for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ithout all the elements, there is no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy could ſubſiſt; and yet this warre amongſt the elements, is the ruine of euery body: in which warre, they are all conquerers, and yet all ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: for the fire dries vp the water, and the water quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the fire; the aire moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the earth, and the earth expels the aire; and yet they haue a mutuall concord: for the fire and aire agree in heate; the aire and water a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in moiſtnes; the water &amp; earth agree in coldneſſe; and the earth and fire agree in drieneſſe; &amp; they all agree in this, that none of them will depart the field, till they haue deſtroyed the ſubiect of their
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18968:41"/> contention which is the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of a man: and in this is to be admired the wonderfull workmanſhip of God. But yet for all this ſearch, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God is not to bee found: for he is incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible; and how can a man comprehend an incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible? He is a Spirit; and how can fleſh and bloud ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend a Spirit? God is infinite, not to be limited in time; he is euery where, and yet no where, either circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptiuely or definitiuely; &amp; how can a man circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed within two yards, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a notion of him, that fils all things, and all places? He is omnipotent; and how can the weake braine of a man conceiue what He is? He is onely good; and how
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18968:41"/> can a man that is onely euill, be able to vnderſtand what He is, that is all good? He is Wiſedome, Strength, Iuſtice, Fortitude, and all Vertue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and morall, yea, in Him are comprehended all Arts and Sciences; what man is, He is; what any other liuing creature is, He is; yea, what is in heauen and earth, He is; for euill, it is a priuation, and therefore is not, nor cannot haue any being in him; and this is all the knowledge man can haue of God, that what he himſelfe, or any other creature is not, that God is; yea, God onely is, and man is nothing but what he is in God: God is in man, and yet no part of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; man is in God, and yet no part of God: yea, God is abſolute without
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18968:42"/> man; man is nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God; and this knowledge of God, as imperfect as it is, is yet ſufficient to direct man to worſhip God, in whom he liues, moues, and hath his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>But how ſhall man wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him whom he hath not knowne? The manner how to worſhip God, which is part of the forme of Gods worſhip, is in truth. <hi>Seneca,</hi> a heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, could make a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction betweene Religion, and Superſtition, or Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,<note place="margin">Religio Deos colit, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitio violat.</note> when he ſayes, That Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is an obſeruation of God in his Worſhip, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Superſtition is a violating of his Worſhip, in drawing it from truth and ſincerity: but what the true Worſhip of God is, man can no way
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18968:42"/> come to the knowledge of, but from God himſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man doth in any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of perfection know what God is. Now there are two Bookes, that God hath giuen man to ſtudy vpon; the Booke of Nature, and the Booke of the Word. In the Booke of Nature, although man may reade ſufficient to condemne himſelfe, yet there he ſhall finde nothing but what will confound him: In the Booke of his Word, God hath beene graciouſly pleaſed more at large to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen himſelfe vnto man, and thereout to affoord him not onely inſtruments, to frame him fit for his Worſhip; but directions how to worſhip him aright. Euery naturall man walkes in darkeneſſe, as
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18968:43"/> is wrriten by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſaiah, 9.2.</note> 
               <hi>The people that walked in darkeneſſe, haue ſeene a great light;</hi> that is, in the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt. The Word, ſayes the Prophet in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.105.</note> 
               <hi>Is a Lampe, or a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne to my feete, and a light vnto my pathes.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſheweth how he got vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and was growne to a hatred of falſe-hood, and errour, namely, by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and Word of God. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> or Chriſt, is ſaid to ride vpon the Word of Truth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.5.</note> as one that would ride in triumph ouer all Hereſie. Now euery man is content to haue ſome forme of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; but this true worſhip doth ſo ſtrictly tie the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to that forme and practcie of Religion, which is
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18968:43"/> taught out of the Word of God, as that a man is ready to frame to himſelfe any kinde of Religion, whereby he might haue ſome diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation for his euill courſe of life, rather then to be held to ſo hard termes: and hence it comes to paſſe, that ſo many fall to Popery, who when they are loth to deny and croſſe themſelues in the luſts of the fleſh, and yet are deſirous to go to heauen, they imbrace this Religion, wherein they beleeue that though they commit neuer ſo great ſinnes; yet if they can get Pardons of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences from the Pope, or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution from the Prieſt, or do ſome workes of Charity, or ſuch as are meritorious in their owne opinion; or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18968:44"/> ſome interceſſion of Saints, or ſome prayers to be made for them after they are dead, they thinke God to be well ſatisfied for their ſinnes, and well pleaſed with them: Nay, ſuch is their groſſe ſtupidity, as that they thinke the ſprinkling of a little holy water, to be ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary for ſoule and body; which appeares plaine in thoſe conjuring words ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Prieſt, in diuine Seruice:<note place="margin">In Manual. ad vſum eccleſiae Sariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burienſis. Exorciſe te creatura ſalis, per Deum <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> viuum. Sis omnibus te ſumentibus ſanitas animae &amp; carporis, &amp; effugiat atque diſcedat ab eo loco quo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſum fuerit, omnis nequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</note> I exorciſe, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure thee, O creature of Salt, that thou beeſt to all that ſhall partake of thee, ſanitie of ſoule &amp; body, and that all euill ſhall depart from that place, where thou art ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. And farther he ſaith, I exorciſe, or coniure thee, O creature of water, that thou
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18968:44"/> mayeſt ſerue to the caſting out of Diuels,<note place="margin">Exorciſo te creatura a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae, in nomine Dei Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ris, vt fias aqua exorciſata ad effugandam omnem pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci, &amp;c. Ad abijcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos daemones, morbóſque pellendos, vt quicquid in domibus vel in locis fidelium haec vnda reſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, careat omni immun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiâ, libere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur à noxa, non illîc reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deat ſpiritus peſtilens, non aura corrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, &amp;c.</note> to the expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of diſeaſes, that vpon whatſoeuer thou art ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in any houſe of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, it may haue taken from it all vncleanneſſe, it may be freed from all obnoxitie; that no peſtilent ſpirit may remaine vpon it, nor any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ayre. Let all the treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the hidden enemy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part: and if there be any thing aduerſe to the health, or quiet of the inhabitants, let it be chaſed away by the aſperſion of this water. And then the Prieſt caſts the ſalt into the water, croſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, after the manner of the Croſſe, and ſayes priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Let there bee an equall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mixture of ſalt and water. And thus is their Holy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18968:45"/> made, and ſprinkled. And who would not be a Papiſt, to haue this benediction of Holy water? And the like benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is there of the Bread. Nay, ſuch is their horrible blaſphemy, as that they hold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wax Candles to be inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, with the light of Gods heauenly Benediction, as they call it, and kindled at the fire of his moſt ſweet clarity; and who would not be a Papiſt, to partake of this light? Farther, ſome of their Prayers for the dead, are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We commend vnto thee, O Lord, the ſoules of thy Seruants, that being dead, they may liue with thee for euer; and what ſinnes they haue fallen into, through the frailtie of their worldly conuerſation, doe thou wipe them away, by the Pardon of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18968:45"/> thy moſt mercifull goodneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another is this, <hi>God, which art the giuer of Pardon, and louer of mans ſaluation; we implore thy Clemency, that thoſe Brothers and Siſters of our Congregations, which are gone out of this world, may come to the ſocietie of thy euerlaſting bleſsing, by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion of the bleſſed</hi> Mary, <hi>for euer a Virgin, &amp; of</hi> Michael <hi>the Archangel, and of all the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third is this, <hi>Make good, we beſeech thee, O omnipotent, and mercifull God, that the ſoules of our Brethren and Siſters of our Congregations, for whom we offer vp to thee this ſacrifice of Praiſe, being expiated by vertue of this Sacrament from all their ſinnes, may receiue the bleſsing of thy euerlaſting light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And who would not be a Papiſt, to haue theſe Prayers
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18968:46"/> ſaid for him after his death, if they were effectuall? The Heathen, ſince they could not be ſo religious to God, as the light of Nature infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them, they ought to be, framed to themſelues gods of men, that ſince they could not, or would not bee like God, they would make gods like themſelues. And thus <hi>Saturne,</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other men, being famous vpon earth, for ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary qualities, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploytes, were called gods af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their deaths. <hi>Seneca</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues, that amongſt Heathen men that worſhipped <hi>Iupiter,</hi> one will haue him to be win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, another will haue him to beare hornes, another ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes him of Adultery, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther complaines, that hee is
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18968:46"/> cruell towards the gods. In all which, ſayes the Authour, they intend nothing, but to take away the ſhame of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from men, who belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſuch gods as theſe, and conceiued it no ſhame for them, to do as their gods did. And hereby appeareth the truth of the Worſhip of God declared in his Word, in that it oppoſeth ſinne: and the reaſon why Idolatry and falſe religion draw away ſo many, is, becauſe they either giue a liberty to ſinne, or a Pardon of ſinne, vpon eaſie conditions; but theſe men which are thus ſeduced, are of another mind, then <hi>Dauid</hi> was, who hid the Word of God in his heart, that hee might not ſinne. He found no ſafety, ſo long as he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18968:47"/> in ſinne, nor any meanes to auoid ſinne, but the Word of God, which is the Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to trie all metals of Religion. If a man doubt of the doctrine of Religion, let him bring it to this Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and he ſhall ſoone diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, whether it be currant or no: If he bring his life, and actions to this Touch-ſtone, he ſhall quickly know, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be good or no: If he bring his faith, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to this Touchſtone, it will quickly ſhew, whether they be ſound, or no: If hee bring his honeſty and iuſtice to this Touch-ſtone, he ſhall eaſily diſcouer, whether they be counterfeit, or no. It is the ſpeciall care of euery good Schoolemaſter, to ſee that his Schollers performe all
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18968:47"/> their exerciſes truly; ſo this Schoolemaſter, the Word, which vndertakes to teach the Worſhip of God, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects to the true Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>And this truth, is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required in the outward practice of Religion, but in the heart and inward ſoule of a man. <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.6.</note> 
               <hi>thou requireſt truth in the inward parts,</hi> ſaith the Pſalme: and it is the complaint of God in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 29.13.</note> That the people drew neere vnto him with their mouthes, and with their lips did ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him, but had remoued their hearts farre from him. A man may be a great Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, well read in all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies, able to diſtinguiſh betweene true Religion, and falſe opinions, well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18968:48"/> and of good vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in the doctrine and diſcipline of Religion, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxall in point of faith, a carefull obſeruer of diuine worſhip, a iuſt dealer amongſt men, ciuill in his courſe of life, well reported of for hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalitie, diligent in all his affaires, true in all his Words, and of a faire demeanor in all his actions: and yet, if this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vprightneſſe to God and man for conſcience ſake of Gods Commandement, be wanting to this man, hee may be wanting of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.<note place="margin">Ioſhua, 24.14.</note> For <hi>Ioſhua</hi> requires the people to feare the Lord, and ſerue him, but how? In ſincerity, and truth. And <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> commands them not onely to ſerue the Lord, but it muſt be done in truth, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18968:48"/> with all their hearts. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion then appeares from the efficient cauſe thereof, to bee the worke of God; from the materiall cauſe, to bee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;<note place="margin">The finall cauſes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the glory of God, and mans ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Nihil ſit fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrà.</hi>
               </note> and from the formall cauſe, to be true, and onely, and properly applied to God. But the Naturall Philoſopher could reach ſo farre, as to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, that nothing could be made in vaine; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if in that inferiour work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of God, in the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of all the creatures, was expreſſed a rare Art; and in this worke, there was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded an end: then certainely, much more in the framing a man after Gods owne Image. Man muſt beleeue an end, yea, a more ſpeciall end, by how much the effect is of a more excellent nature. There
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18968:49"/> are two finall cauſes of Gods Workes, the one communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to man, with all other creatures, which is the laſt, the vttermoſt and chiefeſt end, the other, onely for mans ſake; the former of theſe ends, is the glory of God, to which end he made all that is made, and doth diſpoſe of all things that are done; to which purpoſe are the words in the Reuelation, <hi>Thou art worthy, O Lord, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue glory, and honour, and power, for thou haſt created all things, &amp;c.</hi> If God had not made the world (to our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion,) he had loſt the glory of his power; if he had not made man perfect, he had loſt the glory of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; if man had not fallen (though God was not the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18968:49"/> Author thereof,) he had loſt the glory of his Iuſtice; if he had not redeemed man, hee had loſt the glory of his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; if he had not continued man, he had loſt the glory of his Prouidence; and if he had not beene the worker of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in man, he had loſt all his glory vpon Earth. For to what end was it to make a world, if man had not bene placed as a Gouernour ouer it? To what end was it to make man perfect, but to trie his obedience? To what end was it to continue man, but to wayt for his Redemption? To what end was it to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme man, but to ſerue him in holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe all the dayes of his life? And how could man ſo do, if God had not wrought this
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:18968:50"/> worke of Religion in him?</p>
            <p>Neither is God onely a Creator of man, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in man, to his owne glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; but a louing Father to man, in ſuffering him by this Religion, to worke out his owne ſaluation, which is the ſecond finall cauſe thereof, as the holy Ghoſt ſets it downe in the Philippians, where a Chriſtian is commanded to worke out his ſaluation in feare and trembling. And the Apoſtle to <hi>Titus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Titus 1.2.</note> makes eternall life, the end of all Religion, and godlineſſe; and in this is declared the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull loue of God to man, notwithſtanding his diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in his fall. What man buyes any cattell, but either to droyle them out, or fat them for the Shambles? but
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18968:50"/> this God bought man from death, to life; yea, himſelfe was ledde as a ſheepe to the ſlaughter,<note place="margin">Iſai. 35.7.</note> that he might ſaue man. What Maſter, when he hath hired a ſeruant, bids him imploy his time and labour, to his owne vſe? But this God doth ſo to man, and bids him, if he want ſtocke to ſet vp withall, to come vnto him, and he will furniſh him. What Land-lord, when the Rent-day comes, bids his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant lay out his Rent for his owne beſt profit? But this God, the Land-lord of the World, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man brings him his Rent, which is his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in a religious life, bids him improue it for his owne good, and makes his owne ſaluation, the ſcope and end of all his labour. And is it no
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18968:51"/> leſſe then ſaluation, that a man aymes at in being Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious? Was there euer any man, that had a ſlaue that ran away from him, and ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted himſelfe to his deadly enemy, that would not onely ſpare him puniſhment, but make him a free-man? Yet behold, man that ſold him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as a ſlaue to the Deuill, is made a Free-denizen of Heauen. Was there euer any Souldier that roſe vp in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinie, that did not onely eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape Martiall Law, but was ſent home to inherit the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals owne Land? Yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, man, that did not onely riſe himſelfe, but drew the whole Regiment of Ieſus Chriſt, mankind, into muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; he is ſent to inherit the Kingdome of heauen, Chriſts
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:18968:51"/> owne inheritance. Was there euer any King, that when his ſubiect was conuicted of high Treaſon, would not onely ſpare his life, but make him one of his Priuy Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; or Bed-chamber, where hee ſhould be neereſt to his Perſon? Yet behold, when man had riſen in rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God; he is not onely pardoned his Treaſon, but is receiued into Gods Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Preſence in this world, which is the Church; and ſhall hereafter be made a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy Chamber-man of heauen. Why then, is it to no end to be Religious, when he ſhall not onely thereby promote the glory of his Creator, but purchaſe to himſelfe an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Manſion in that new Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem?</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:18968:52"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The effects of Religion, Obedience, Sanctitie, and Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note>Neither is this Religion which proceeds from ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent cauſes, without the like effects, amongſt which, theſe three may be noted; Obedience, Sanctity, and Wiſedome. Obedience is either actiue, or paſſiue. For actiue obedience, God in his Couenant declared to his Children, by his Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> promiſeth firſt to worke Religion in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>A new heart will I giue you, and a new Spirit will I put within you;</hi> and what followes vpon this? <hi>Then</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>you ſhall walke in my ſtatutes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 36.26.</note> 
               <hi>and you ſhall keepe my Iudgements and doe them.</hi> But this practicall obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience muſt be generall, ſuch as is inioyned by God in the Propheſie of <hi>Ieremiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 11.4.</note> that they ſhould obey his voice,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18968:52"/> and do the words of his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, according to all that he had commanded them. And God threatens his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Leuiticus, that if they would not doe all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, then he would appoint ouer them terror, conſumption, and the like, <hi>Curſed is he that doth not abide in all, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 26.14, 15, 16.</note> It is farther requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that this obedience ſhould bee conſtant; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon our Sauiour grounds his promiſe, <hi>That hee that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth to the end,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.13.</note> 
               <hi>the ſame ſhall be ſaued.</hi> And it is the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that Chriſt propounds to his Diſciples, in the Goſpel of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.31.</note> 
               <hi>If ye continue in my Word, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ye my Diſciples indeed.</hi> Paſſiue obedience, is to ſuffer with patience, all the afflictions that befall a
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:18968:53"/> man: for <hi>Paul</hi> hath giuen eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Chriſtian his doome, where he ſaies,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>All that will liue godly in Ieſus Chriſt, ſhall ſuffer perſecution:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt exhorts his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to poſſeſſe their ſoules in patience;<note place="margin">Luk. 21.19.</note> of which Dauid is a ſingular example in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the curſe of <hi>Shimei;</hi> when he ſaies,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.10, 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Let him curſe, becauſe the Lord hath ſaid vnto him, Curſe;</hi> and makes an excuſe for <hi>Shimei,</hi> by way of extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating his fault, ſince his owne ſonne that came forth of his bowels, ſought his life: and in concluſion, caſts himſelfe vpon the Lord, <hi>It may be</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>the Lord will looke vpon my affliction.</hi> Neither is it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſuffer calamity, but to be humbled vnder Gods hand in time of diſtreſſe,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:18968:53"/> which is the admonition of <hi>Iames, Be afflicted, and mourne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 4.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>and weepe, humble your ſelues in the ſight of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next effect of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is Sanctity; the ſpeech of <hi>Paul</hi> to the Theſſalonians,<note place="margin">Theſ. 4.1, 3, 5, 6.</note> is this, when <hi>we beſeech you brethren, that as ye haue receiued from vs how ye ought to walke,</hi> (that is, in the way of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) <hi>and pleaſe God, ſo you would abound more and more; for this is the will of God, euen your ſanctification.</hi> And this ſanctifying conſiſts either in the forbearing ſinne, to which purpoſe, the Apoſtle in the ſame place inſtanceth in two euils, from which they ſhould abſtaine, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the luſt, and concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, or vncleanneſſe, and fraud, or deceit: or elſe it
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:18968:54"/> conſiſts in the practice of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe; to which end God would haue the children of Iſrael to weare frindges on their garments,<note place="margin">Num. 15.41.</note> that they might remember and do all his Commandements, and be holy vnto God. And <hi>Peter</hi> ſetteth God, as a Patterne of holineſſe, exhorting them as obedient children, to be holy in all manner of conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.14.15.</note> as he that called them, is holy: and indeed this holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is a maruellous effect, whereby is wrought ſuch a ſecret alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert, as that none knowes how it comes to paſſe, but his owne ſoule within him, which yet himſelfe is not able to expreſſe, neither would any one take him to be the ſame man he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18968:54"/> Is it not a ſtrange thing to find a man, that for twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, thirty, forty yeeres toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hath ſwoom in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of all earthly things, hath denied himſelfe no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of pleaſure that is to bee found out vnder the Sunne; hath had the generall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of all that knew him, for an vnderſtanding, a iuſt, a temperate, and a liberall man; hath had continuall health; hath neuer knowne what the leaſt miſery is? To ſee this man all on a ſudden, in the middeſt of his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, perplexed, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled within himſelfe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the miſerable eſtate he is in; laying to his owne charge, blindneſſe of mind, iniuſtice of his actions, a want of gouernment in his
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18968:55"/> courſe of life, and neglect of charitable workes, accuſing himſelfe of all manner of ſinne, and finding no comfort at all, till the ſame power hath raiſed him vp, that before had thus caſt him downe; and then to ſee him changing his vaine company, diſregarding his ſuperfluous wealth, laying aſide his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable and time-conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming pleaſures, contemning popular applauſe, labouring for the true knowledge of God, and of the meanes how to ſerue him aright, perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming all good workes in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God; which before he obſerued onely in a ciuill reſpect, and abſtaining from thoſe euill actions for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, which (haply)
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18968:55"/> before he had forborne the practice of, for ſome ſiniſter, or outward regard, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſanctified vſe of all Gods bleſſings, as of health, peace, libertie, and the like: Is not this a wonderfull alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is found in euery man, ſo ſoone as true Religion en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into his heart?</p>
            <p>The third effect of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is Wiſedome; &amp; this is either Sapience, or Prudence.<note place="margin">In definition. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ethic. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Sapience is defined by <hi>Plato,</hi> to be a ſimple or incompoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Science, or the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Diuine and Eternall things, or a knowledge that proceeds from contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the cauſe of things. And <hi>Aristotle,</hi> his Scholler, defines Prudence to be a true habit working with reaſon,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:18968:56"/> vpon thoſe things that are, good or euill to a man: but the chiefe Preacher and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of Wiſedome, hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded them both in one verſe, where he ſaies, that Sapience is the reuerence of God, and Prudence the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, as <hi>Tremel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> interprets it, ſo that out of a true knowledge of God, infuſed by God himſelfe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds this reuerence of God, which is Sapience, and the vertuous carriage of a mans ſelfe towards men, eſpecially the Saints, is Prudence. The obiect of Sapience, is <hi>ens,</hi> or being, and the obiect of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, is the chiefe good. Now God is the onely Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or I AM; and he is the chiefe, yea, the onely Good, and therefore Religion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:18968:56"/> the true knowledge and worſhip of God, workes this Wiſedome in a man. There are foure things which accompliſh a mans happineſſe, pleaſure, profit, honour, and long life to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy them in: all which <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> comprehends in Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, where he ſaies, that <hi>All other delights of a man are not to be compared vnto her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>and length of dayes is in her right hand, and in her left hand riches and honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there is no ſpeaking of any thing vnder God,<note place="margin">Man, the ſubiect of Religion.</note> but it muſt haue a place of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. So Religion muſt haue a ſubiect to reſide in, which is man that hath beene ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten named. And here Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſits like a Queene in her Maieſtie, ſhe keepes her Court in the ſoule of man,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:18968:57"/> and her chaire of State, is the heart of man, ſo that to man may be well ſaid, <hi>Let your doores ſtand open, you euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting gates, and let the Queene of glory come in.</hi> She is ſo wiſe of her ſelfe, and ſo powerfull, as that ſhe needes no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, onely ſhe hath continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally waiting vpon her, two Secretaries of State, and a Recorder or Regiſter, the firſt of theſe Secretaries is Vnderſtanding; to this ſhe referres the examining of all ſuites preferred, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of what nature they are. The ſecond Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is the Will, and to this ſhe referres the returning of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to all Petitions made: the Recorder to this great Queene, is Memory, and here are regiſtred all Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions, with their anſwers, to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:18968:57"/> the end that man might not be without a preſident for whatſoeuer he ſhall be a ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; if here he can find, that ſuch and ſuch things haue beene to ſuch and ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, at ſuch and ſuch times, and in ſuch and ſuch a place gtanted, he may haue hope to obtaine his deſire in that kinde: but if he finde, that ſuch things haue beene deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and thought altogether vnfit to be asked, or granted, let him deſiſt from Petitions, in this nature. In this office of the Memory, likewiſe are recorded all the Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents that euer haue bin gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto any man; ſo that if he chance at any time to loſe his euidence, or aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, here he may take out a new Copie of it when hee will. In this Office likewiſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18968:58"/> are entred all the Actions of man, that if at any time hee haue done any memorable ſeruice, hee may craue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, (for this is a bountifull Queene,) or if he haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any crime, he may ſue for his Pardon; for God that hath placed Religion his Vicegerent vpon earth, is a mercifull God. Now the houſhold ſeruants of this Queene, are the affections, ſo that where ſhee commands to loue, the Religious man loues; where ſhe commands to hate, he hates; where ſhe commands to reioyce, hee reioyceth; where ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to ſorrow, he ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes; where ſhe commands to feare, he feares; where ſhe commands confidence, he is bold: ſo that all the actions are ready at her command.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:18968:58"/> The common ſubiects of this Queene, (for ſhe admits no Peeres in her Dominions,) are all the parts of the body; the eye, the eare, the hand, the foote, and all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of a Chriſtian mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy are gouerned by her, and receiue protection, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from her; ſhe feedes the hungry mouth, clothes the naked backe, ſtrengthens euery weake part, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaines the whole. The reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue of this Great Queene, is all that a man hath in this world; no ſooner was ſhee entred into the hearts of the Chriſtians in the Acts, but they came and laid all they had at the Apoſtles feete: where ſhe bids Giue, man muſt giue; yea, if ſhe call for his children, or himſelfe, hee muſt bee ready with the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:18968:59"/> which <hi>Seneca</hi> reports <hi>Demetrius</hi> to make to the gods:<note place="margin">Seneca, <hi>lib.</hi> cur. bonis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris mala fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt. Hanc quoque animoſam Demetrij for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimi viri vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem audiffe me mominiſſe hoc vnum, inquit, Dij immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, de vobis queri poſſum, quod non an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè mihi vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram notam feciſtis: prior enim ad iſta veniſſem, ad quae nunc vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus ſum. vultis liberos illos vobis ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuli? vultis aliquam par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem corporis? Sumite. Non magnam rem promitto, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to totum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſpiritum? quidni? nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam moram faciam, quò minus recipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atis quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtis: à volen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te recipietis, quidquid pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieritis. quid ergo eſt? ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offerre quàm tradere. Quod opus fuit anferre? accipere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuiſtis, ſed ne nunc qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem auſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, quia nihil eripitur niſi retinenti.</note> There is one thing, O ye immortall gods, I haue to complaine of you, that you would not let me know your pleaſure before-hand, for I would haue firſt offered my ſelfe, to what I am now cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by you: will you haue my children? I haue bred them vp for you: will you haue any member of my body? Take it: I promiſe no great matter; for within a ſhort time I ſhall leaue the whole. Will you haue my life? what elſe? I will make no delay to hinder you from receiuing what you haue giuen: you ſhall willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiue whatſoeuer you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: I had rather offer all to you vnasked, then deliuer it to you being demanded: you ſhall not need to vſe any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:18968:59"/> you may take them: nothing is ſaid to be taken, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from him, that doth not withhold it, and I deny you nothing: where ſhee bids Keepe, man muſt keepe; if ſhe call for all a man hath, he muſt part with it: if ſhe bring ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo great an increaſe, ſhe muſt haue the diſpoſing of all; yet ſhe does not alwayes turne her Tenants out of poſſeſſion; onely ſhee will haue them know, that they are but Tenants at will: and as this Religion is onely an adiunct to man (no man hath it borne with him,) ſo it is a ſubiect to diuers adiuncts.</p>
            <p>The adiuncts of Religion,<note place="margin">The proper adiuncts of Religion, knowledge, faith, loue, and feare.</note> are either proper, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: the proper adiuncts of Religion, ſome of them may be theſe; knowledge, faith, loue, and feare.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:18968:60"/>
            <p>This knowledge, which is a proper adiunct of Religion, is not an Hiſtorical knowledge, but a ſauing knowledge, ſuch a knowledge as is taught by him that workes Religion in the heart; which our Sauiour verifies,<note place="margin">Mat. 1 1.27.</note> in ſaying, <hi>That no man knowes the Father but the Sonne, and he to whom the Son reuealeth him.</hi> And this was the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that <hi>Paul</hi> was infuſed withall,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.4.</note> when he was caught vp to the third heauen: ſo that it is wrought together with Religion, and without which there is no Religion. The Philoſopher obſerues a twofold knowledge;<note place="margin">A priori &amp; poſteriori.</note> the one proceeding from the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent cauſes, which are for the moſt part vnknowne: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the ſubſequent ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and adioyning quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and the latter of theſe,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:18968:60"/> is all the knowledge a man can likely haue in naturall things; but this is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine diſtinction in Diuinity, wherein both parts are to be noted for the naturall man, by obſeruation, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and diſcourſe, may, out of effects and qualities, gather ſome knowledge of God and his Diuine being, and a worſhip to bee due to him, and an infinit power to be in him, and he may grope out ſo much (according to the words of the Author of the Acts of the Apoſtles) as will direct him to ſeeke out the true knowledge of God and his worſhip,<note place="margin">Acts 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; but this ſauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge here ſpoken of, is ſuch a one, as that no man can haue it in him, without the ſame God that giues it, reueale it
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18968:61"/> to him out of thoſe hidden principles wrought in the heart of man, which are not poſſible to be expreſſed.</p>
            <p>The next proper adiunct is faith, which is ſo linked to the former of knowledge, as that who hath not the one, hath not the other; and who hath not true Religion, hath neither; and therefore the Apoſtle ioynes them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as things vnſeparable, and infallible tokens, or ſignes one of another; where he exhorts the Corinthians to try themſelues whether they were in the faith, or no; but how ſhould they try themſelues? by no way, but by their knowledge; and therefore he asks them in the next words,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>Do you not know your ſelues?</hi> and ſhewes them farther, how they come, by
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:18968:61"/> this knowledge, namely, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Ieſus Chriſt was in them, except they were Reprobates.</hi> Is it not a ſtrange thing, that <hi>Herod</hi> ſhould ſend the Wiſe men to the Phariſes, to informe themſelues where Chriſt ſhould be borne, and they could direct them to Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and ſhew them what had beene propheſied, and yet could not beleeue in him? But this ſhewes the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and faith grounded thereupon, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to the Apoſtles by Chriſt himſelfe; and that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Phariſes, which is none of this ſauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or faith which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to Religion.</p>
            <p>The third proper adiunct of Religion, is loue, and that loue is not euery loue, but
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:18968:62"/> the loue of God, and our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren for Gods ſake, which loue is wrought in man, by the ſame Spirit that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelfe is wrought: The Apoſtle ſaies,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>That the loue of of God is ſhed abroad into our hearts, by the holy Ghoſt, which is giuen to vs.</hi> And in another place; hee acknowledges great thankes to be due to God, for the increaſe of faith, and abundance of loue, which was in the Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.3.</note> where hee ioynes faith, and loue, as the gifts of God, that go alwayes together: neither let a man deceiue himſelfe in this loue of God: for many men thinke they loue God, when indeed they loue onely themſelues: as Chriſt vpbrayded them that followed him onely for loue of the loaues. Diuers Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:18968:62"/> people haue worſhipped the Sunne, the Moone, the Starres. <hi>Ceres,</hi> the goddeſſe of Corne, <hi>Bacchus,</hi> the god of Wine, and the like, for the benefit they haue receiued from theſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and no queſtion, herein had ſome generall notation of a deitie: but this loue of God, which flowes from true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, muſt not be onely a loue of him for his goodneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, no, not for that great gift of ſaluation to mankinde, but a loue of him, becauſe he is ſo holy, and abſolute perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yea, though we receiued none of theſe mercies, yet this Religion will cauſe vs to loue him, for himſelfe, and his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in obedience to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion they all haue in Chriſt; which is deliuered by <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Epiſt. Ioh. 3.21.</note> in theſe words, <hi>And this comfort
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18968:63"/> haue we from God, that he who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth God, loueth his brother alſo.</hi> And the Communion which all the Saints haue in Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the loue, which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to the Epheſians<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.15.</note> ſaith, <hi>Is the knitting of the ioynts of Chriſts body, from whence it receiueth growth, and is built vp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt of the proper ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncts, is Feare: and this againe muſt bee the Feare of God, which feare is neuer ſeparated from true Religion; nor euer to be found where true Religion is not. In the Scriptures Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Religion are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times taken in the ſame ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and therefore it is ſaid, <hi>The feare of the Lord is Wiſedome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 28.28.</note> And when a man is ſaid to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh that great worke of his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, which is an end of his Religion, he is aduiſed by the <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.3.</note>Apoſtle to do it in the feare of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18968:63"/> the Lord. Religion conſiſts in the obſeruing of the Law of God. Now, to feare God and obſerue his Commandements, is the ſumme of the Law; but without the feare of God, there is no keeping of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, and that makes a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat obedience. It is not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment that a man muſt onely feare, but feare God, becauſe he is God; yea, though there were no puniſhment for offending him; and feare the committing of an euill act, becauſe it is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to him, and contrary to his pure nature, which feare in the Corinthians is called the perfection of holineſſe: and theſe foure qualities of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, faith, loue, and feare, are ſo linked together, as that they are not to be found one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out another, but make a golden bracelet to adorne Religion
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:18968:64"/> withall; for out of knowledge a man muſt be able to giue a reaſon of his faith; as <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.15.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts; and loue is the efficacie of faith,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> affirmes: and true feare is diſtinguiſhed from ſlauiſh feare by loue; as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by comparing the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of <hi>Zacharias,</hi> which ſaies, <hi>That we being deliuered out of the hands of our enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.74.</note> 
               <hi>might ſerue him without feare;</hi> with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. ve. 119.120.</note> who profeſſeth that he loued the Teſtimonies of God, and his fleſh trembled before him, and hee was afraid of his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Zacharias</hi> frees ſuch as are redeemed by Chriſt,<note place="margin">Q. d. non quidem à prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia tua metuo vt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Gen. <hi>3.</hi> nam contra illam mihi adeſſe expeto, ſed ab infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutate mea ne prouocem iudicia tua.</note> from a ſeruile feare: but the Pſalmiſt ſheweth what cauſed a childlike feare in him, namely, the loue of Gods Teſtimonies. <hi>Tremelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> &amp; <hi>Iunius</hi> render this expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the feare ſpoken of by
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:18968:64"/> the Pſalmiſt, it is, as if he had ſaid; I feare not thy preſence, (O God) as <hi>Adam</hi> did, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, I wiſh thee alway with me: but I feare my owne weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, leſt I ſhould prouoke thee to iudgement. So that a Chriſtian man may bee ſaid to beleeue in God, becauſe he ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually knowes him; to loue him, becauſe hee beleeues in him; and to feare him, becauſe hee loues him.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe proper adiuncts of Religion,<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncts of Religion, all morall vertues.</note> there are common adiuncts of Religion, in the number of which, are Zeale, &amp; Mildneſſe, and Patience, and Temperance, &amp; Iuſtice, and all morall vertues: for though theſe do not ſo neerely depend vpon Religion, as the other do, yet where there is true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, theſe are in ſome meaſure to be found. For Zeale, take the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:18968:65"/> opinion of <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4.18.</note> 
               <hi>That it is good to be zealous alwayes in a good thing.</hi> For Meekenes, take the words of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 2.34.</note> 
               <hi>Surely God ſcorneth the ſcorners, but giueth grace vnto the lowly.</hi> For Patience, take the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 21.19.</note> 
               <hi>In your patience poſſeſſe ye your ſoules.</hi> For Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, take our Sauiors inquiry, and bleſſing,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.45.</note> 
               <hi>Who is a faithfull and wiſe ſeruant, whom his Lord hath made ruler ouer his houſhold, to giue them meate in due ſeaſon? Bleſſed is that ſeruant, whom his Lord, when he commeth, ſhall find ſo doing.</hi> For Iuſtice,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.9.</note> take <hi>Noah</hi> for a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne: <hi>Noah was a iuſt man &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in his generations, and walked with God.</hi> And for all manner of morall vertues, there are Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, Promiſes, and Examples to bee found in the Scripture, which directs all men to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>And now, out of what hath
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:18968:65"/> gone before, there may bee a geſſe giuen what this Religion is, which is taken vpon them by many, but found in few. To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine Religion from its eſſentiall cauſes and internall, is not ſo eaſie; it being a difficult thing to find out the matter &amp; forme of elementarie ſubſtances, and diſtinguiſh betweene them and their properties: much more hard then muſt it be, preciſely to ſet forth the matter &amp; forme of incorporall ſubſtances, and moſt difficult to giue a definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the eſſentiall cauſes of a ſpirituall thing; yet from what was taken before, to bee the matter and forme of Religion; this definition may bee giuen;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Definition of Religion.</hi> Zanch. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. Theſ. <hi>1.</hi> vera religio quae idem eſt quod <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in vero dei cultu poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta eſt.</note> That Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God. It is firſt worſhip: it is ſecondly, the Worſhip of God in truth; and this is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of <hi>Zanchy:</hi> but where a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:18968:66"/> definition may not be eaſily ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, a deſcription may giue more light; and a deſcription of Religion may be this: That Religion,<note place="margin">A deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion.</note> is the true Worſhip of God, wrought by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in man, by meanes of his Word, which worketh in a man, Obedience, Sanctitie, and Wiſedome; and is ſeated prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally in the ſoule of man, whence it diſpoſeth of, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth all the faculties of the mind, the actions of the body, and the whole eſtate of man to Gods glory, and the ſaluation of man, and is alwayes accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with ſauing knowledge, a liuely faith, loue of God and his Saints, and feare of God, and all vertues Spirituall and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, in ſome meaſure: and this deſcription is gathered out of all the conſentany artificiall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of Logick. There was
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:18968:66"/> a Heathen man that deſcribes Religion to bee that,<note place="margin">Cic. <hi>2.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. Religio qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuperioris et iuſdam natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ram (quam diuinam. vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caut) curam caeremoniem que aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt.</note> which workes a care, and ceremonious obſeruation of ſome ſuperior nature, which, ſaies he, they call Diuine: but this man ſeemed onely to point at the outward forme of Religion, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was all the Religion they had. <hi>Caluin</hi> in one place, ſaies,<note place="margin">Cal. in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. ſuper <hi>2.</hi> Cap. Iohan Vera antiqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> religio, quae in Chriſto ſundata eſt.</note> that true, and ancient Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is that, which is founded vpon Chriſt, where he ſeemed to direct onely to the true foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; wherupon the doctrine of Religion was to bee groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, namely, Chriſt Ieſus.<note place="margin">Mel. de ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plicibus the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matibus reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio conſtat eſſe cultum Dei.</note> 
               <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton</hi> defines Religion to bee the Worſhip of God; and though indeed God is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, but rather diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, where he is not truly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped: and ſo this definition may ſtand compleat; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe moſt pretended Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:18968:67"/> acknowledge a Worſhip of God: and many Learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines haue made a definition betweene true, and falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: and this <hi>Melancton</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in a deſcription hee makes of Religion, ſaies, that Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the Worſhip of God, which conſiſts in the feare of God, and beliefe in God; inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in that deſcription, two of the proper adiuncts, before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. In theſe regards, truth may not bee altogether ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluouſly called, part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of Religion; and yet is it not to be conceiued, that the forme of Religion is to be deuided; but truth to Godward of that worſhip, (which was taken to be the matter) may be receiued to mans apprehenſion, as a forme of Religion: and if theſe things are all true, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo many claimes laid to
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:18968:67"/> Religion, as there are, yet it will appeare, that Religion is not ſo conuerſant in the world, as euery man would haue it.</p>
            <p>It were to be wiſhed, that men would not reſt content with a bare name of Religion, deceiuing themſelues, whileſt many of them thinke to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue others: certainely, ſome women that vſe to paint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue that the colours which they vſe for that purpoſe when they once are laid on by them, are the natural coluors of their faces: for elſe, why ſhould they be proud, except it be of their skill in painting? So men that haue put on a guiſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, imagine themſelues to be ſuch as they outwardly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be: for elſe why ſhould they glory in it, except it bee of their art in hypocriſing? <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſus</hi> ſeeing himſelfe in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:18968:68"/> fell in loue with himſelfe, and was turned into a Flowre; ſo a man, when he lookes vpon himſelfe, in the waterie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of his owne ſwimming fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, is ſubiect to grow in loue with himſelfe, who yet ſhall proue but a fading flowre, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly conuerting to rottennes: but if he view himſelfe in the Chriſtall Glaſſe of the pure Word of God, he ſhall appeare before Regeneration, to be a Leper, a Swine, a Dogge, a Diuell; yet notwithſtanding, when this bleſſed forme of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is put vpon him, he ſhall be here like <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man after Gods owne heart; and in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, conformed vnto the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Sonne of God, his elder Brother, and Sauiour, Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18968:68"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
